So, now we're going to start building things
with gates. Gates are our new low-level building
blocks. So, the first thing we're going to do is
add some numbers with gates. And we're going to
basically use a pattern much like this, except
that this little adding hand calculator does
numbers from 0 through 9. We're going to do the
same thing with just zero and one. So, they're
going to do base two addition, but we're still
going to do things like carry. So when we click
over to the next one, it carries and goes on to
the next number. And so we're going to solve the
carry problem. At this point, you should know the
truth tables for not and and or exclusive or. Now,
not and and or are kind of like what you've done
in programming for a long time now. Exclusive or
is just kind of weird, meaning that it's a more of
a counter than an than a simple or, which means if
one of them is true, the output is true. And if
one both are zero or both are one, the output is
zero. And of course, NAND and NOR are just kind of
inverted versions of and and or. So at this point,
I think you should be able to fill these in. And
I probably won't need to explain these to you much
more, but we do want to represent numbers larger
than zero and one. That would that would be kind
of a limited range. So what we use is we use base
two numbers and we take different wires and give
them different values. And so in base two, there's
a one's position, a two's position, a four's, and
an eight's position. And so you can think of three
wires can represent a number from 0 through 7.
So in base 10, 123 is 1 * 100, 2 * 10, and 3 * 1,
which adds up to 123, which is kind of redundant.
But if you look at base 2, 1 1 0, that's 1 *
4, which is 4 plus 1 * 2, which is 2 + 0 * 1,
which is 0. 4 + 2 = 6. So to convert 1 1 0 b 2
into base 10, it's 6 b 10. We're going to make
things simple for now. We're not going to make you
generally be able to convert any base 10 number.
As a matter of fact, for most of the rest of this
section of the class, we will never encounter a
number higher than 0 through 8. Mostly, it'll
be 0 through 7. And then once in a while,
we'll carry and into the eight's position. So, we
represent the four's position, the two's position,
and the one's position. So, 1 1 0 equals 6.
But you can quickly say, oh, that's a four,
that's a two, and no one, which is 4 plus two
equals six. So you can quickly convert from that.
So the idea of having one wire represent the the
ones of a number, another wire representing the
twos of the number and another wire representing
the fours of the number is how we can represent a
number from 0 through 7. So in this example that
I've given you, the tw's wire is a one and the
four's wire is a one and we hook that to a Nixie
tube. Remember Nixie tubes? The Nixie tube shows
decodes the ones, twos, and fours and converts it
to base 10. So if we're putting in two zero 1's,
one twos, and one fours, well that's 2 plus 4
equals six. And the Nixie tube has the logic to
simply display that. So if we can send it a set of
wires, three wires, it will show us the base 10.
And in order to help you have a good understanding
of quick conversion from base 2 to base 10,
at least for numbers between zero and seven, I've
got a little game called the Nixie challenge that
both converts base 2 to base 10, base 10 to
base 2, and adding of base two numbers. Now,
speaking of adding base two numbers, let's
start at the very beginning. 1 + 1 equals 2.
That's true in base 10, but it's not true
in base two because you don't have the digit
two in base two. So 1 + 1 is zero, carry the
one. Just be like 5 + 5 is in base 10 is zero,
carry the one or 10. So 1 0 base 2 is two because
that's a one in the two's position and a zero in
the one's position. So remember 1 + 1 equals 0,
carry the one. You see the same pattern when you
do 2 plus 2 = 4. 0 plus 0 equ= 0. 1 plus 1 equals
0. Carry the 1. And again, the same thing happens
when you do 4 plus 4 equals 8. And so now we've
seen our first number greater than seven. 4 + 4=
8. Now you got to carry. You got to ripple carry.
In the 3 + 1= 4 example, 1 + 1 equals 0. Carry the
one. Now in the second column, you got to add that
carry. the carry one plus the top one equals Z,
carry the one. So now we end up with 1 0 0 or
four. And so these carries can cruise along.
Um 3 + 2 equals 5. You can see there's a 1
plus 0 = 1. 1 plus 1 equals 0. Carry the 1,
which gives us 1 0 1, which is a 4 and a 1, which
is five. And then the last one, which is seven.
All ones, which is a four plus a two plus a one,
which is seven. Seven plus one. You start with 1
plus 1 equals zero. Carry the one, but then
the carry plus the other one is zero again.
Carry the one again. And then the carry plus the
one is a zero. Carry the one again, and then you
end up with the one. So 7 + 1 equals 8. So the
logic that we do here to do one of these columns,
so just the the the columns is a thing we call the
half adder. And half adder is a logic circuit that
takes as its inputs the A and the B and as output
comes up with the sum and the carry. Now for now
we're only thinking about one column of addition.
0 plus 0 is 0 carry the zero. 0 + 1 is 1 carry the
zero. 1 plus 0 = 1 carry the zero. 1 plus 1 equals
0 carry the one. So if we look at the circuit,
the circuit is a combination of the and and an
exclusive or. And if you look at the two columns,
you look at the sum column. The sum column 0 1 1
0 is just the same as exclusive or and the carry
column is just the same as the and. So we simply
take the A and the B both to an exclusive orgate
and both to an ANDgate and out comes a sum and a
carry. So two gates gives us a half adder. So if
we look at the different values 0 + 0 equ= 0 carry
the 0 1 + 0 = 1 carry the 0 and 1 + 1 = 0 carry
the 1. So this solves one column of addition. But
if you think about one column of addition other
than the first column there's also a carryin and
that's how we solve it with the full adder. So the
full adder its truth table has a carry in a sum
a sum b and then a car sum total and a carry out.
So operands a and b a carry in sum and carry out.
So the if you get a carry in that's a one. If you
get a a of one and a b of one well that is three
which is the sum is one carry the one. So that's
a little different right? So now we have up to
three numbers. It's kind of like a counter of
three bits, right? And it's showing us that. But
we have a carry-in, A and B, and then a sum and a
carry out. Okay? And so it's pretty much what you
would expect. Um, you can think of the sum and the
carry out is like the carry out is kind of like a
two when you're carrying to the next column. Okay?
So let's take a look at the circuit that needs to
solve this problem. A full adder compensates for
a carryin. So we call a full adder a full adder
because it really is two half adders plus a little
bit. So if you look at the section that's the A
and the B that's just a half adder. It's got an
exclusive ore and an and. And then what we have is
a another half adder at the top. Exclusive or two
and and two. And the input to that half adder is
the carry in plus the output of exclusive or one.
Exclusive or two produces the overall sum of the
three numbers. And then we have to add an orgate
that takes the output of the A and B and as well
as the and and we or it all together and get a
carry out. And you can look at that or as did we
generate a carry out by A and B or did we generate
a carry out because A or B was one and the carryin
was one and that's what that or is doing. So it's
probably best to take a quick look at how this
works with a working circuit. So here is a full
adder circuit. And so we're going to start and
work through carry in A and B and then the sum
and the carry out. So we're set them all to zero.
So the sum is zero. So let's just exercise this
as a half adder for example. So if we make AB one
then we get a sum of one and a carry out of zero.
And if we make BB be one then we get a sum of zero
and a carry out of one. And so the carry-in is
not participating in any way. This is just a half
adder that's working. So now if we add the carry
in. So now we have carryin of one, a of one, b of
one, and sum is one and carry out is one. And now
you can pretty much put any combination of ones
and zeros. And this is kind of a counter where
the carry out plus the sum is like how many carry
in is one and a is zero and b is one. we kind of
have two ones and so we get a carry out of one and
a sum of zero. That's kind of one zero which is a
two. Okay, so that's a full adder. It's basically
two half adders plus an orgate. Now that we built
this full adder and we won't go into too much
detail here, but this carry out was designed to
become the carry-in for the next digit. So if we
look at 2 + 5 = 7, we can see the the full adder
has the a a for the ones column and the b for the
ones column. A for the tw's column and b for the
tw's column and a for the four's column and b
for the four's column. And so because a is two,
a1 is zero, a2 is one, and a4 is zero. So 0 1
0. B is five and so it's 1 0 1. So B1 is one. B2
the two's uh two's column of B is zero. And the
four's column of B is one. And so they just go
into these full adders. And when we say full one
in here, that is those gates that we just got done
describing. And they have a sum out and that goes
to our ultimate sum. But the carry out of each
column goes to the carry in of the next column.
That's what's clever about the full adder. So this
is a ripple carry. the carry is rippling from one
column to the next on the screen. It's the top to
the bottom. So you just copy the you connect the
carry outs to the carry into the next full adder
and then that full adder has a carry out and
away it goes. Now if you look at the third one
you have the carry out that indicates an overflow
indicator and that is this can only handle numbers
from 0 through 7. But if you add 5 + 5, that's
bigger than seven. And the overflow indicator,
we're like, "Oh, now we just figured out how to
take three full adders and make a threebit adder."
So this is a three-bit adder with the A's on the
left hand side, 0 1 0 or two, and the B's on the
right hand side, one 0, one or five. And you can
see the adder has a seven. We put a little little
display in there so you can see the number seven.
and it has sums coming out the bottom and it has
overflows coming out the top. And so this is
part of how digital logic works is that we
build something cool like a threebit adder that's
made up of three full adders which each full adder
is made up of two half adders plus an orgate. But
we don't have to draw that. We just say give me a
three-bit adder and away you go. And so we can
quickly build abstractions that are all really
cool reusable componentry. And so we only build a
full adder long enough to build a three-bit adder
to build then a three-bit adder component. And so
we can build these things pretty rapidly. And now
you can start to see how we might eventually build
a microprocessor. At least now we have a three-bit
adder. And if you listen carefully, maybe go back
and watch this again. If you look at it carefully,
you'll see you know if you go all the way back,
you know how many transistors that you could make
a three-bit adder. But it would be a bunch
of them. It would be a bunch of them because
remember an and an ANDgate is four transistors
plus the knot which is two transistors. So an
ANDgate is six transistors and that's just
an ANDgate. So you you figure out after a
while that building gates and then building
reusable components, you know how to build them,
but you don't have to know how to build them
to use a component like a three-bit adder in
a circuit. And that's the fun of it all. And
we're going to keep doing this as we go forward.